[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
um I just want to go very briefly
over the two slit experiment again I
don't think we ever quite finished so
let me finish that discussion the tlit
experiment and we made a very
simple uh version of the two slit
experiment there's a
source we I called it an electron it
could be a photon it could be any kind
of particle
whatever but let's call it an electron
since I'm used to it the electron is
emitted from The Source now if you like
you can imagine that the electron can be
emitted from any one of several
places uh there is a barrier to the
electron over here here with some
openings again the openings could be in
any one of any uh several places but for
Simplicity let's just suppose that there
are only two
openings
um I don't remember what I call them
last time I think I might have called
them plus one and minus one I hate that
that doesn't sound good uh so let's
let's call them A and B this time A and
B I think I think I call this point
zero and the rest the electron can go
through the little hole at a you can go
through the little hole at B and just
imagine that the rest is blocked off so
that if an electron hits any one of the
other sites for Simplicity you can just
pretend that it gets uh that it gets
reflected
back if it arrives at a it can go
through the slit and arrive somewhere at
the final end over here and I think I
labeled those points by integers so this
could be the MTH site over
here zero site would be over here m = 1
2 3 -1 - 2 minus 3 and so
forth and we'll start an electron over
here so initially we haven't discussed
very much how States change and we're
going to do that not tonight I don't
think but um but eventually we will but
the most important thing is that States
change in a linear way that means if you
start with a linear superposition of two
states with coefficients what it evolves
into is the same linear superposition of
whatever any one of them evolved into so
if for
example uh well let's start let's start
we start with an electron in state zero
incidentally for the present purposes
the electron has no spin we don't have
to worry about the electron spin that's
that's irrelevant for the moment it just
is at a place and so the states of the
electron are simply
characterized by which one of these
vertical positions they're
at so we start the
electron right at the center at point
zero it
evolves and it evolves into a linear
superposition of States at A and B the
electron has no particular preferred
reason to go to either A or B and let's
suppose it's nice and symmetric so it
has equal amplitude equal amplitude to
get to A or B so zero goes
to
a plus
b right what does a plus b mean it means
a
state uh in which the electron could be
at a you could find it with a
probability a half at a and you could
prob and you could find it with a
probability B probability a half at
B and it's just a Quantum superposition
of the two
configurations now when it gets to a it
then if it gets to a it then moves on
and it moves on to the screen here so we
can say that
a evolves into some superposition
arbitrary superposition nothing special
a sum on
N of some coefficients which represent
the probability amplitudes s
subm of the electron now being at the
MTH
place that's what happens if you were to
have started the way you can think about
it is to get the whole B all together
start an electron at a and wait a while
and it will arrive at a superposition of
states with different amplitudes size
subm M or if you started at B it will
also Evol and I think I
called the coefficient here f m *
m okay so let's uh let's first begin
with one hole completely closed the
electron can only go through
a if it can't go through b all together
we can forget this we close it up and
the probability that the electron
arrives at the M site here is just going
to be SAR MS m and
we I'm focused on the M site don't worry
about any of the others just the
amplitude that the electron gets to
point m is s m and the probability that
it gets there we can just call PM is SAR
mm that's assuming it goes through the
root
a in other words a if we have blocked
off whole
B maybe we should give it a name maybe I
should stick an a over here indicate
that it went through the opening
a likewise if I close up the whole a and
open up the whole
B then the probability is f star
m
f now in classical logic classical
statistics classical uh probability
Theory statistical mechanics if you had
a beam of particles
uh which was uh not uh made with enough
Precision so you know with some uh with
some uncertainty in it some of the
particles might go through a some of
them may go through b but our
expectation would be that the
probability to get to M would be the sum
of the probabilities of going through a
or going through b we would just add
those probabilities not so in quantum
mechanics in quantum
mechanics where we have to write is that
if we start at a we get to here if we
start at B we get to here but if we
start at a plus b if we start with the
state a plus b which the
electron is sort of equally between
these two then what we have to get to a
plus
b will go
to summation of
n s subn * n
oop I subm * m I
guess some
M plus f subm * m and I can just
represent that by adding s to F so it
just becomes sum of s m plus 5
m *
m all right let's let's forget for the
moment the sum let's just focus on a
particular Point
m not even interested in the sum here
just focus on a particular Point M what
is the probability that the electron
gets to M and the answer is the square
of this amplitude or the square it times
its complex conjugate and so the answer
is p m the probability to get to M when
both A and B are both
open is s well just square that out
which will give four terms SAR m S M
plus F star m f
m plus SAR m f m plus s m f star
M all right so the answer is the sum of
the two original probabilities plus an
extra term and the extra term is called
the interference term the interference
between the two TR
trajectories one of them going through
the upper hole and one of them going
through the lower hole this is no analog
in any kind of classical uh statistics
this extra term and to see how weird it
is I mean for example if if M happened
to
lie right on the Symmetry Point
here then you'd expect SII and fi to be
equal by Symmetry and this would give
you four times the probability of going
through either
ho it's not hard to arrange by going off
center here
you can find well you can either go
through off center or you can do other
little tricks uh in the beam of
particles here to make S Min equal to
minus fi and then you would just get
zero probability so despite the fact
that the electron can get to M through a
or through b if you open a and if you
open a and b in that particular
Circumstance the electron just won't get
there as I said that's as weird as
anything I know in quantum mechanics and
it's very very
simple uh but now comes a question which
we started to talk about last time I
think we may have even finished it but I
want to review it again what happens if
somebody actually is present and
actually watches whether the electron
goes through one hole or the other and
even records whether it goes through one
hole or the other then what happens
surely then you must know whether the
electron went through a or b so we made
up a uh a little
system we added another element here we
added a spin the spin can either be up
or down it could be the electron's spin
itself there's no reason why it couldn't
be the electron spin but I simply wanted
to think of it as an external uh um
measuring apparatus that could record
the presence of the electron so I didn't
want to think of it as part of the
electron let's not think of it as part
of the Elon we add another degree of
Freedom over here which is a spin which
can be up or down up or down and let's
not ask exactly how it happens but when
the
electron passes through the hole a
there's no there's no spin at B when the
electron passes through the hole at a
whatever it does is it gives a kick to
the spin and it flips it that's an
assumption an assumption about the way
this spin is located what it how it
interacts with the electron we measure
over and over again that when the
electron does pass by the spin it does
kick it over so we know what happens an
electron passing by the Spin kicks it
over kicks it from let's say from down
to
up all right now let's reanalyze the
experiment we don't just have an
electron we have an electron and another
spin so we have to add something into
the state Vector here we can't just
describe it as as an electron at Point Z
but we have to describe it as an
electron at Point Z with the spin
down or our apparatus unactivated we can
think of it as the apparatus being
unactivated uh and so that's our initial
state if the electron goes through the
upper
hole then it becomes State a the
electron is at Point a
but the spin gets flipped
up if it goes through ho B the spin
doesn't see the electron and it stays
pointing
down so now we have something new the
two states A and B are correlated and
entangled with a spin they're entangled
with a
spin such that by measuring the spin you
can tell whether the electron went
through the upper hole or the lower
hole well what happens to a
up once a once the electron departs from
here it no longer interacts with the
spin assume and so I assume that it will
not kick the spin over again and so all
that will happen is a will evolve
exactly as a evolved before except the
spin will remain
up this this is not a measurement though
this is a measurement
are we collapsing a wave packet M and
collapsing the wave packet simply means
destroying the interference pattern no I
mean at at A and B when you're changing
the spin
possibly you're flipping a spin yes that
constitutes a measurement of the
electron and it constitutes a collapse
of the wave packet of the electron when
thought of as the composite system of
electron and spin no it doesn't collapse
the wave packet the only way to collapse
the wave packet of combined system is
for something else to look at
it to get
collaps two through two things in there
um if you had collaps a away packet you
would have Au plus BD you would don't
have one of the other no you for it no
no no no collapsing the wave packet is a
language to use if you don't want to
remember that there's this other spin
there then you forget the other Spin and
you just say the wave kak got collapsed
to either A or
B by the presence of the spin by the
presence of the spin but if you keep the
spin present if you keep the spin
present in other words if you include
the apparatus into the Des into the
description then you don't talk about
collapse of the wave packet you talk
about establishment of entanglement
it's just simply the spin it could be
anything it could be a pointer that has
two states it could be the emission of a
photon so that up so the down could
stand for no Photon and up could stand
for a photon being present so it could
be anything which distinguishes which of
the two holes it went through it's
different I mean even if you didn't have
the spin you might it go through the top
or the bottom it interacted with this
metal this metal aperture that had two
holes yeah I mean there was the question
is whether it a mark on the uh on the
metal on the metal okay now the answer
is yes it could leave a mark
but it could leave a mark but that
depends that depends on details of this
metal plate that's there and in
particular if the metal plate has an
energy gap if it takes some energy to
excite it and the electron is low energy
it may not have enough energy to excite
the uh the uh
uh the um anything interesting in this
system
here and so it will not leave a
mark but that's the criteria that
doesn't leave a mark okay let me let me
say this I was sort of say well it's
going through and it has some momentum
to get the as opposed to way up high but
maybe we're
not but we yeah but you don't have a
spread so you have a spread of momentum
States in A and B but it's the same
there's no difference
are you asking
whether are you asking whether you can
tell which hole the electron went
through by looking at the
recoil uh yes okay good good let's take
that care good the electron goes through
the upper hole and obviously it gives a
little kick upward to the uh if it goes
through the lower hole it gives a little
kick downward right so it changes the
momentum of the screen here all right
now the we we're getting a a little bit
ahead of ourselves into uh into a little
more complex situation obviously but let
me tell you what the answer is the
answer is that the that the screen here
itself has an uncertainty in its
momentum that because it's localized in
space through the uncertainty principle
which we haven't talked about uh the
screen here or whatever we call it the
barrier the barrier is well localized
because it's well localized it has a
spread in its momentum so it looks like
this
now that's the momentum space uh
distribution that's the probability
distribution for momentum and it's
pretty well spread and the reason it's
pretty well spread is because the
location is very very nicely definite so
it's pretty well spread then the
electron goes through the upper hole if
it goes through the upper hole it gives
a little kick and it shifts this
distribution a little
bit if it went through the lower hole it
would shifted the other way a little bit
but you can't tell uniquely and in fact
as long as the as long as the kick is
small by comparison with the spread in
the momentum space wave function here
you basically uh it's it almost
completely overlaps with it and you
don't get kicked into an orthogonal
state of the uh of the motion okay so
that's that's a very very good question
and but there is a very very good answer
yeah I saw it last week there can be a
case where you're not you're not purely
in up or down right right so that's
right it's exactly the same thing as if
instead of saying when the electron goes
through here it kicks down to up instead
it kicks it to all almost down plus a
little bit of
up or the other way whatever and you can
and that will allow you to have
different
degrees of destruction of the
interference pattern but I want to take
the extreme example now where you do a
complete measurement where you do an
absolute measurement which means that
you establish a complete correlation
between A and B on the one hand and up
and down on the other hand so that by
looking at the spin you can determine
completely and uniquely which of the two
holes the electron went through that's
the uh that's the notion if you like of
a experiment of a of a of a measurement
of a measurement establishing an
entanglement between a system and an
apparatus the apparatus just being the
spin okay so let's just uh let's just do
the
uh dot all the eyes and cross all the
t's and now in this situation let's see
B we never finished
here B did not kick the electron up so B
if the electron goes through b the spin
stays down and it just continues to stay
down so now we have a state as I said
with a uh with this
entanglement between the wave function
of the electron SII or fi on the one
hand and up and down on the other hand
all right let's just go through the
formal the very formal motions of
calculating the probability that the
electron is found at Point
M so there are two ways that the
electron could be found at M it could be
found with with the electron at M with
the spin up or electron at M with the
spin down so what we have to do is build
the projection
operator onto the state where the
electron is at Point
M remember what the rule is if you have
some property that you want to represent
by a projection operator you take the
Subspace corresponding to that property
you find a basis of orthogonal states in
that Subspace and then you build the
project ection operator as a sum of
diads uh sum over all the all the uh
basis vectors in the
Subspace of
the diad composed out of them all right
what are the states in which the
electron is at M what there are two
states there's
M
up M up and this m down M down that's it
those are the only two states in which
the electron is found at
M so this is the projection
operator onto the state onto the
configuration where the electron is at M
so now what we have to do is we have to
take the final State what is the final
State the final state is the sum of
these
two add these
together now we cannot factor out M up
and M down and right it in this form
here because each one multiplies a
different C Vector so I IM multiplies
one C Vector s fim multiplies another C
Vector all right let's let's actually
let's just do it let's uh fite the
bullet and do the whole thing M up I
need more room M up plus M
down M down that's the projection
operator
let's put something around around it now
we take the state Vector the state
Vector uh is
um
uh some on
in
here that's a summation index there sum
on in N
up s in plus f n
and
down likewise on this side over here we
have the same thing size star
in oops so star in in
up plus five star in N
down brackets around all these things
all right now first of all there are the
non-cross terms the non-interference
terms the terms like s star s let's just
look at them
uh San
here this piece here has an up elect has
an up Spin and it can only combine with
the up spin over here it's orthogonal to
the down Spin and so the in a product of
an up with a down zero you only get a
contribution from Up with up and
furthermore you only get a contribution
when n is equal to
M the inner product of Up N is only non
zero with M up when n is equal to n when
m is equal to n and then the inner
product is
one okay so out of here you pick out the
single term where m is equal to
n likewise from this side M has to equal
n and up has to equal up up otherwise
you don't get a contribution so from the
direct terms you get SAR m s
m okay and also similarly F star M
FM okay that one comes from this term in
the projection
operator but you get nothing from the
cross term the cross
term coming when you try to combine a
Down with an up up here can only go with
up here but then the up over here will
kill the down over
here so the projection operator does not
allow you to combine a SII with a fi
because these spins are orthogonal in
the various terms all right so here's
the result the result is that if you do
a
measurement the result is the sums of
the probabilities exactly as you would
have imagined In classical physics so if
you don't look at the root that the
electron takes and if nothing looks not
just you but if no Mark is left that you
can ever or anybody else can ever
determine afterwards whether the
electron went up or down or through the
upper roote or the lower route then
there's an interference pattern
yeah probably where
here
no above this
probably uh probably
yeah where is it over here
yeah yeah yeah but the main point is the
main point is you've got to you've got
to match not just
whoops I he's the one to
S uh you've got to match not only the
ends but the uppy down of the of the
state vectors and that will cancel or
kill or destroy the interference
patterns between
and so can you say at the bottom that's
just the sum of two single experiments
on top of each that's right it's exactly
the same as if it was classical
classical statistics
[Music]
yeah then there's an interference
pattern in other words that means that
you have to add amplitudes if there's a
if this
yes what's that oh you get EX if you
sorry if you put the spin B you K the
Elon a and kick the electron kick the
spin yeah good okay let's suppose right
let's suppose the spin is located in
some symmetrical situation let's say
over here where it gets equally kicked
uh whether it goes through a or b then
when it'll come out let's see where will
it come out over here then uh then we'll
just have a a up plus let's see up yeah
a up plus b up right and then it'll be
exactly as if uh then there'll be an
then there will be an interference
pattern in the end you will not be able
to tell from the fact that the spin is
up which hole it went
through so
if if
um
good then we that would leave us in this
situation right the way you're telling
finally you measure the spin of the
El well I don't have to do any I do not
have to measure the spin of the electron
the electron has
measured the electron has done the
measurement the electron has done the
measurement not of the electron spin the
electron has done the measurement of
which hole it went through I don't have
to look at the electron I sorry I don't
have to look at the
spin to know that the interference
pattern will be destroyed I don't
actually have to look at the electron
just the fact that the information is
recorded by a system I could look at it
but just the fact that it's recorded and
it's recorded uh in uh in the
orthogonality of up and down that's
enough to destroy the interference panel
so I don't have to look at the electron
I just look at the electron sorry I keep
saying electron I don't ever have to
look at the spin I just look at the
electrons coming through
I have a beam of electrons coming
through I do this over and over again I
send through an electron do the
experiment electron arrives somewhere
and then I put the spin back in its
original position do the whole
experiment again put the spin put the
spin back in its original position do
the whole experiment again and gather
statistics of what the probability is
that the electron arrives in different
places I never actually have to look at
the spin
uh all I have to do is look at the
electron and see where it came out and I
will discover that there was no
interference
pattern
yeah
scen then that will also destroy the
interference yeah uh that's right um if
the or another
yeah basically if the momentum wave
function of the screen here is narrow
enough so that when the electron goes
through it gives it a kick and kicks it
to a configuration which is orthogonal
to the original configuration then it
will destroy the interference pattern
right in fact there's another way that
interference patterns get
destroyed if the electron now this is
subtle this is very subtle but if the
electron goes to the upper hole
here then it may and it's a slow
electron let's say it's a very slow
electron not too fast it will emit some
radiation every time an electron is
accelerated and it has to be accelerated
to go from here to here it will emit a
photon right so or it may emit a photon
it may emit a photon not that it will
emit a photon it may emit a photon if it
goes through the lower hole it also May
emit a photon the probability of
emitting a photon in accidentally by
electron is very low it's about one part
in 100 for a low energy electron so only
one part in 100 uh uh does it emit an
electron so it does leave a little bit
of information in the radiation field
but with only emitting an a photon one
part in a
100 you cannot be certain when you look
at the system and discover there was no
Photon emitted you cannot be certain
which hole it went through but on the
other hand and if you really whip the
electron through there fast in other
words a high energy electron and you
really arranged it so that the electron
went through one hole way up on top and
the other hole way on down on bottom so
that it really had to whip around and
accelerate a
lot then the likelihood of emitting a
photon would be larger and the
interference pattern would be more
destroyed so just the ability to emit
photons is enough to partially destroy
interference patterns and does yeah so
when you actually do the experiment you
have to perform statistically large
number of absolutely in order to build
up the data set yes from which in fact
you infer the probability distribution
yes because you can abolutely your
ability to approximate the probability
distribution is a function of how many
experiments ELR so what you're saying is
that in the case of an electron
probability of emitting a photon which
in principle be detected that is one
source of
noise exp yeah one one source of
interference one source of destruction
of the interference pattern you can call
it noise if you want well what you see
practically is the experiment from a
theory point of view says
those detector statistics will contain
dark and light areas areas of the
detector where you get
you don't get but in fact if you can get
A1 contrast you did really good and
there's going to be some residual um
number of particles that show up anyway
in the soal dark or forbidden
areas so my question is this if you have
a large number of these things and you
have a A system that maybe reads this
what you're saying is any
possibility of determining after the
fact which the electron went through
that will destroy the yes yes but you
may also have a situ a partial situation
where you by looking at something you
may be able to say it was more probable
that you went through the upper hole and
the lower hole Yeah that's easy to do
for example as I said when the electron
passes through here instead of kicking
down to up it just kicks the uh it just
kicks the direction of spin a little bit
so that it's mostly still down and just
a little bit up that will partially that
will destroy the interference pattern a
little bit it'll blur it a little
bit Yeah would you say the
one
of yeah what you could do is you could
collect statistics only for those events
in which a photon was
emitted okay and then you would find the
interference pattern uh worse now it's
not quite completely clear because if a
photon if if a photon is emitted from
here it may not be completely orthogonal
from a photon emitted from
here uh the way function of the photons
may not complet be orthogonal so you can
still have a little bit of blurry uh
blur situation there but you know I mean
you can destroy interference in many
many ways just the atmosphere and this
is this is the this is the biggest
source of interference destruction in
particular why don't you see me as fuzzy
why do you well I assume you don't see
me as fuzzy I mean I start out here and
you don't you you close your eyes CL
close your eyes everybody close your
eyes Okay and now open them you find me
in the same place you don't find my wave
function having spread out all over the
place in fact you could wait forever and
ever and ever and you would not see my
or the moon the moon's wave packet
doesn't uh doesn't
spread part of the reason is part of the
reason is the moon is heavy but the
other reason is that it's constantly
bombarded by Atmosphere by other things
and so it's as if it's continuously
measured and every time it's
measured um if you continuously keep
measuring a
thing uh it will not spread uh at all
side suggestion here on your course next
whenever you teach it yeah I'm using
terms like collapsing weight packet you
talking about measuring you just gave us
a theory of measurement that's that's
something that's would be good to teach
in a course teaching
well
forget well you're saying things are
always interacting with one another so
well I'm trying to give you an extremely
precise example all right I give you an
extremely precise
example and now we can extrapolate from
that we can we could work out some other
examples we could work out some other
examples in which partial experiments
are done uh I I think those are
straightforward but I'm trying to give
you crystal clear
example uh where there's no ambiguity so
that you can see the mechanism by which
the interference pattern is destroyed
and tangle what forces you to to do that
I mean you know 30 40 50 years ago you
can sort of get away with Loosely not
worrying about it too much yeah well I
mean even you know I mean except for the
Final
Consequence question but collapse of the
wave packet and collapse of the wave
packet here means collapse of this wave
packets which literally means that you
throw away the off diagonal terms the um
the the mixed terms the five side
terms that is
you can describe it that way say I did a
measurement I collapsed the wave packet
but you also ought to be able to
describe uh the composite system of the
electron and the detector in a way that
doesn't involve any uh any uh you know
Hanky Panky with collapsing wave packets
and so forth the corresponding correct
description of a composite system is
entanglement took place so that's what I
uh that's the importance of entanglement
in doing measurements and obviously it's
a very important uh part of
nature
question I don't know if this is
relevant or not if it is not relevant
just ignore it but you said that Photon
will get emitted because the path is
curved just in the theoretical case
there was a gravitational field present
so that it's actually a straight line in
the gravitational field how would that
change the
situation wa say again let's see like
the path from Z to A to m is curved yeah
so for that reason for well I mean there
is no well- defined path but you can
more or less see that
that
that the electron had to accelerate to
go around the corner here right so now
if there was a mass sitting between A
and B oh if there's a mass sitting
between so that it's actually a natural
path yeah would it change the situation
you just have one of the
deflection wouldn't change it yep you
could have one of the slits not be
deflected but then the other one would
be
uh good look we can think of a thousand
million variations on this theme the end
of the story is if anything tags the
leaves a mark telling you which way the
electron went that destroys the
interference pattern it'll destroy it
partially if it gives you some
probabilistic information about which
way the electron went not certain
information but uh but um biased uh
toward One Direction or the other I have
a question um does this U definition of
interference contradict anything we
learned in continuum
electromagnetics multiple photons
interacting with each other and
geometries and so forth is is it the
same thing is it another way to look at
the same thing or is it radically
different um the interference pattern
here when there are many many electrons
or let's say many photons to to make it
simpler when there are many many photons
coming through all at once the
interference pattern is nothing but the
interference pattern of wave motion of
wave uh wave you know electromagnetic
wave
Wes uh the fact that it also happens for
electrons tells you that there's some
sort of wave associated with the
electron it's not the electromagnetic
waves it's the electron wave
function okay let's move yeah one more I
just had a question about the missed
last class parameters of the beam are
that has an equal chance of being
emitted with a momentum that would put
it between a and well it's it's yeah
yeah oh which which would put it between
A and B
yeah well we're just assuming that that
if it arrives anywhere in between it
just bounces off that uh that this
region is closed off yeah yeah it's
blocked off
yeah unless
no no no the cat is not in a superp
position of alive and dead okay the cat
is not in a superp position of alive and
dead that's exactly what is not true
what what is true is the cat is
entangled with another system what is it
entangled with uh the question of
whether the bullet was fired or not so
it's a composite system let's say it
consists of a of a gun
and cat so it's a composite system gun
and cat and the gun can be in two states
the two states are unfired and
fired okay the cat can be in two states
Dead or
Alive okay you start with a live cat and
an unfired gun U for
unfired and then something happens and
you wait a while and after a while the
system evolves into live cat with some
coefficient alpha live cat unfired gun
plus some other coefficient dead cat
fired
gun okay it is not in a
superposition live plus
dead it's in an entangled state with the
gun all right so you cannot do any kind
of interference experiment between live
and dead if you were to calculate the
probability of live and dead you would
have you would have no cross
terms uh it's the the the gun itself the
firing of the gun has left a mark of
firing or not firing you don't the point
is you don't have to look at the cat to
find out if it's alive or dead you can
look at the gun so that tells you it was
entangled and it is very much it's
basically exactly the same mathematics
as
this no the cat in stringer's experiment
is not in a superposition of alive and
dead the composite system is in a
superposition of live unfired and dead
fire one
[Music]
more I think you're been very careful to
talk about D struction of the
interference pattern as being something
different from a measurement which is
what goes on at the fin no no I'm saying
when a measurement takes place it
destroys
okay well it exactly
but my my question is really what goes
on at the final screen that lets us talk
about probabilities rather than
States let say it again what happens
what could why at the final screen can
we reduce this all the
probabilities rather than having to
caring the entangled States
for well look we
there is a probability postulate in
quantum mechanics and you construct the
projection operator and take its
expectation value and that's the
probability I don't know what to say
beyond
that
uh what happens is you get the
interference pattern or you don't and
and that's that's well okay I set up
some experiment here and now why am I
can I talk about
the
screen and not at the
middle say it again why do I talk about
the probability of the of the electron
being at the screen and in some position
and not talking about going through a or
b you can talk about it well you don't
want to talk about it at A or B unless
you measure it if you measure it you can
then go and ask this spin did it go
through here or didn't it go through
here and you will have a probability for
it having gone through here having gone
through here now what about at this end
at this end at some point you have to do
a measurement as to where the electron
was in other words you the electron has
to do something at this end to record
the fact that it has arrived at one of
these positions we haven't talked about
that I just said it either arrives at
one of these positions or it doesn't but
if it arrives at one of these positions
another kind of measurement can happen
the other kind of measurement would be
the black blackening of a uh or it could
be we could for example put a spin at
every one of these
SES if the electron arrives at that
point it flips the spin up if it arrives
at this point it flips this spin up in
other words at the end of the day I am
imagining that we do some experiment
over here to find out where the electron
arrives I've sort of suppressed that
part of the
experiment uh of the same thing as as
just putting more barriers
you had a cation screen that will give
off the photon and then the electron
continues on you would then have it
Ricochet in some unkown direction and
you would again have a situation where
sure sure but I mean to complete the
experiment you actually have to measure
where the electron is measuring where
the electron is means that some sort of
Mark is left on the system by where the
electron arrives over here it could be
because there are spins aligned along
here or it could just be because when
elect R arrive on photographic plates
they blacken the uh spot on the on the
plate uh and we look at the black spot
we don't actually look at the electron
we look at the black spot but the black
spot becomes entangled with the position
of the electron along here I think the
answer is you're
position oper
yes yes yes but the process the process
of separating a system into that which
is measured and that which measures is
always ambiguous you can
always uh say all right look the
experiment really doesn't happen until I
look at the
spin in that case you would add another
element where you could either just say
this combined wave function here
collapses or you could add another
ingredient in me and me also has two
states me having seen spin up and having
recorded it in my brain and me having
seen spin down and recording that in my
brain so we could uh we could say once I
look at this it evolves into something
even more complicated a up and me having
seen up plus be down and me having seen
down but then you could be watching me
okay the point is there's a degree of
consistency there's a degree of
consistency that the probability to find
either uh A or B with up and down is the
same as the probability of a up me
seeing up B down me seeing down so at
some point there's no there's no point
in going further in entangling anybody
else in the experiment but if you did
you would still have consistency
in the case in the shing's cat face is
more than the gun that's entangled with
the cat there's smoke in the Box smoke
in the Box all but then but then but
then schinger is on the outside of the
box and he's not entangled but then he
looks in and he sees one or the other
and so Schrodinger himself becomes
entangled with the Box the gun and the
cat and the process and then wigner
who's waiting outside he's going to ask
Stringer what did you see he becomes
entang the whole world is a highly
entangled thing because they all
correlated each other but they're
correlated in the consistent way
yeah yeah there's no interference
there's no interference if uh
unless unless there's been nothing to
record which thing happened yeah one
more one more we're going to we want to
move on doesn't the uncertainty
principle figure into this now the
process of measuring affecting the event
being absolutely
um well one particular instance of it is
uh the you as was pointed out you might
worry that The Recoil of this screen
here might ruin your measurement by
leaving a mark as to whether you went
through the upper hole or the lower hole
it's the uncertainty principle and the
uncertainty of the momentum of the uh of
the screen
here which um doesn't allow you to uh to
determine unambiguously which hole the
electron went through so certainly
uncertainty principle plays a role here
you know the the the most important
thing to to well not the most important
thing necessarily but what you should
keep in your mind is that the difference
between a classical experiment and a um
and a
uh and a quantum mechanical experiment a
classical experiment you always imagine
an classical experiment can be done in a
gentle enough way that you can find out
what you want to find out without
disturbing the system okay without
disturbing uh the state of the system
here you can see that we have definitely
Disturbed the state of the
system uh the measurement is not done
until the entanglement has been
established and establishing an
entanglement is a significant change in
the state of a system and a measurement
is not done until that entanglement is
established once that entanglement is
established it changes the answers it
changes the answers whether for example
there is or there isn't a interference
pattern so classical physics you always
imagine that you could make your
experiment gently enough that it doesn't
influence in any way the system that
you're studying or perhaps in a in a in
arbitrarily small amount of uh uh change
in the system whereas Quantum
mechanically you are forced to to in
order to do an experiment to establish
an entanglement and that's a big change
that's a significant change in the
system yeah um what about the distance
between a and b and let's say it's
arbitrarily large effect does that have
on the interference P well that depends
on that depends on your assumptions
um uh
nothing particular I don't think I don't
think there's anything
particular of course what it will do is
it will make the probability of going
through either of the holes very
small so both the size and the fs will
be very very small if you take the holes
to be very far away the overwhelming
probability will be that it hits the
wall and gets bounced back chances of it
getting out the very far distances may
be very much smaller so it might uh but
but uh but apart from that I don't think
it has any special effect yeah it it
seems really lucky that all this
superposition is linear mhm well I don't
know was lucky but
uh is that really fundamentally true or
is that yes it's fundamentally true took
no no no no no no no
no well that's another question but
uh we've talked about this over and over
again and I keep telling you I don't
know the answer except I know from
experience how hard it is to uh to
modify things a little bit uh so I'm not
going to answer that question because I
honestly don't know the answer it's an
it's an empirical fact and it's the
basis of quantum mechanics but it's not
it's not easy to make a logically
coherent story of a slight bit of
nonlinearity it becomes a mess now
there
well really it's the replacement of one
kind of logic by another it's the
replacement of log the logic of
classical sets by the logic of
subspaces
why the Lord in His Infinite Wisdom
decided on subspaces instead of
something else uh maybe the Reverend
Haggard knows but I don't
excuse
me
what consider
theity
proceeding detect the target being this
yeah such that we would perhaps be able
to determine the trajectory which it
pass through after the event whether
there was interference or not do that
change results well I think what we
could do is we put another we could put
another set of detectors over here and
ask about interference over here is that
what you're is that the sort of thing
you so I was at first considering would
there be some way to put a detector an a
based on some effect that would happen
later in time you know but there's
really not a way to do that and then it
occurred to me that is there a way
perhaps after the target where we
checking which way the electron went
through well all I can say say is if
there is something left in the system
that allows you to determine but
typically no I mean if the if it got
passed here without leaving any mark on
the system when it gets here uh
offand not really
no but if if there is a way to detect
which way I went through that will
destroy the even if that detction event
would happen after
yeah yeah as I said you don't even have
to do the detection as long as the
detection is implicitly uh I mean the
order well you mustn't violate causality
cause must precede effect so other than
that uh yeah our measurement obviously a
have been chosen for the impact Target
but if we were able to based on moning
after it get that point deter which way
it went
through uh I guess I guess we will have
to set up a very specific experimental
situation and analyze it because I can't
analyze in the abstract uh without
having a very very definite concrete uh
example in front of
me well the bubble chamber on the other
side wouldn't tell you which hole it
went through on this side
would not not in general
no say it
again
yeah Oh you mean if the trajectory
remembers which uh which uh way the
electron went through if you have a
bubble chamber over here well let's
say
iMed over
here big bubble chamber little bubble
chamber I would say it covers the whole
thing okay so big bubble
chamber
yeah okay then what well does it that
would ITA destroy the oh
absolutely absolutely
absolutely certainly for sure
yeah's automatically
no interference as soon as it
reach well it's
constantly just just to be precise about
it we could put a a thin wall of bubble
chamber here and then afterwards the
electron arrives over here and we look
over here and we see do we see a track
over here or do we see a track over here
the answer is that anything that
anything that leaves a track will
certainly destroy the interference
pattern for sure
but you got it on the opposite side of
the tget from what I was say so I guess
maybe the real
answer well as I said each example has
to be analyzed separately but the rule
the rule is very general if there is a
mark left on the system from which you
can
deduce the degree of ambiguity will
determine will determine the uh the
magnitude of the effect but say which
you can deduce unambiguously which of
the holes the electron went through then
there will be no interference pattern
and that's that's the most General way
of saying it now you can think of all
sorts of examples and uh and but always
trace it back to that ask whether there
is or there isn't anything left on the
system which remembers and always bring
it back to this here do you get
situation where you I'm trying to figure
out how to get out of this situation
why each other yeah okay so at some
point you are able to perform the
experiment where you do get
interference what is it that causes you
toe
uncertainty whatever
it uncertainty in for example in the
momentum of this screen
here that's what you're talking about
previous history
previous
[Music]
to
well
that everything is entangled already
it's not no it better not be entangled
already you have to start with you have
to start with some systems which are
disentangled Let's uh let's move on
let's move on and we can and because
this I understand
why it's difficult to move on there's a
zillion infinite number of questions but
I think it's a good idea Having learned
the
rule go back and do the exercises
yourself see if you can figure out
yourself uh the answer to some of the
questions because they're they're good
questions it's not they're not good
questions but I think we can go on and
on and on forever and ever
I by making a measurement by making a
measurement you actually do some
disentanglement for example by making a
measurement of the electron over here
you for all practical purposes you start
over again and you start over again with
the electron definitely over here that
electron is now from your perspective
you throw away the other possibility
having seen the electron having seen the
spin up you simply forget this one here
you forget it all together and you say
aha the electron is over here let's
start over
again and now you can now you can say
this electron uh this electron is over
here and what you start with is the
state a up a up is not an entangled
State okay you just throw this one away
you see I made me my measurement I
looked at it I saw that this one that
the spin was up so I know that the
initial starting point was a up and I
throw away the other
uh yeah that's right that's right so we
could that's right so we could uh we
could uh make a the experiment more
complicated we could put
another uh pair of slits over here and
uh start with the electron starting at
this point and the spin would play no
special role anymore it was simply the
thing that told you that the electron
started over here well something told
you the electron started over
here and so it really was in some sense
entangled with the uh with the electron
gun or whatever it was that started the
electron moving so it's it's sort of a
nested hierarchy of different uh levels
of discussing the problem as I said the
division the
division here's your
system here's your
detector here's somebody looking at it
here's somebody looking at looking at it
and so forth and so on and so on and way
you draw the line between the system and
the detection is ambiguous but depending
on where you draw the line at some point
you will have to say the wave function
collapses right in observe but in
observing this entire system
here you won't say that the electron
wave function collapses you will say the
combination of wave function of electron
detector and schinger or
whoever uh is collapsed by wigner making
a experiment
on this was a cat I guess cat gun and
shinger
you get the idea and the only question
is whether it's consistent whether it's
consistent um whether at the end of the
day when Schrodinger comes to wigner and
says what did you see me think and
wigner says I thought I thought I saw
you think that the cat was
dead and schinger says yes that's what I
saw the cat was
dead uh that's consistent and quantum
mechanics is hooked up in such a way
that you don't run into inconsistencies
in this manner
let's move on let's move on let's move
on let's move
on we've talked about
entanglement well we want to take a
break we have not gone as far as I had
imagined we would but that's fine no
that's that's not a
problem
uh well let's keep going a
little entropy I want to discuss entropy
really what I'm going to discuss is how
do you define a measure of the degree of
entanglement between two systems if I
have two electrons and both their spins
are up they're not entangled you learn
nothing about one uh by looking that
looking at the other there's no there's
no sense of looking at one and finding
out some piece of information you didn't
know about the
other
uh so that's not an entangled state two
spins both
up generally unentangled states are
called Product States and in product
States each of the subsystems by itself
has a very well- defined state that uh
that uh you might as well disregard the
other one
altogether but they can get entangled
they can get entangled and the amount of
entanglement is a quantitative measure
of it there many quantitative meas
measures of entanglement but the one
we're going to talk about and the usual
one is called entanglement
entropy so I want to I want to explain
what entanglement entropy is it is the
thing if you want to find out
whether some description of a composite
system involves entanglement the test is
to calculate the entanglement
entropy all right so first of all let's
talk about classical entropy what what
is classical
entropy um imagine we have some system
and the system has some collection of
States classical now we're doing
classical so logic is Boolean algebra
it's just a classical set theory there's
the space of all possible states of some
system and let's take the states to be
discreet so there's some finite number
of states let's call number of states
capital
N now entropy is not just a property of
a system it's a property of a system
together with your state of knowledge
about the system in other words it's
something that has to do with both you
and your state of knowledge on the one
hand and the system
itself the less you know about a system
the more its entropy the more you know
about it the less it's entropy according
to the definition of entropy that we're
going to talk about all right so let's
see how come we how can we quantify that
uh all right so this capital N States
and let's suppose that what we
know is that the system is
in one of little n States one of little
n States capital N is not going to play
any tremendous role for the moment all
we know is that the system is in one of
little end states with equal probability
with equal probability for all those
little n
States then we would say we're ignorant
and our degree of ignorance is little n
little n it could be in any of little n
States the bigger little n is the less
we know about the system right if we
knew that little if if little n was just
one in other words that would be the
situation where we know exactly what the
state of the system is and it's in one
of the states one known known state of
the system then we would say little n is
one in that case we would say the
entropy is zero we have no ignorance we
know everything there is to know about
the system and so there is no no uh no
um ignorance what if little n is Big N
if little n is Big N it means we know
nothing about which state the system is
in that corresponds to the maximum
entropy all right so let me give you one
definition of the entropy which is good
for this situation here it is simply by
definition logarithm it's called s and
it's the
logarithm of the number of
states uh that your ignorance allows
shall I say little n is all you know is
that it's in one of little n States then
the entropy is simply logarithm of
little
n um
you're probably wondering why you take
the
logarithm anybody know why you take the
logarithm yeah you multiply numbers of
States you add entropy that's that's uh
that's one way of saying it another way
of saying it let me give you another
example supposing my system is again a
system of
spins uh and uh I know something about
uh a whole bunch of them ups and downs
and ups and downs and so
forth and I know nothing whatever about
the system I know nothing whatever about
the system how many possible states are
there well the answer is two to the
number now another completely different
n two to the number of spins how many
spins are there let's call them m m
spins 2 to the m is the total number of
states and what's the logarithm of two
and um if I knew nothing at all about
the system then in here would just be 2
to the m any one of two to the M's uh
States the logarithm of the number of
states would just be proportional to M
so what the logarithm measures is the
number of bits of information a bit
being a spin right the number of bits
now a bit basically means a two-l system
the number number of
bits uh is the number of bits but the
number of bits gets exponentiated to
determine the number of states and it's
just a useful definition to go back to
the logarithm which is basically a
measure of the number of uh little bits
of information and number of yes no or
the number of up down
decisions that is contained in your
degree of
ignorance okay so in any case that's a
definition s is equal to the L arithm of
n now what happens if you have a more
General situation instead of
having uh oh incidentally in this case
here the probability let's write down
some probability the
probability let's call these states I
all right let's say the probability for
I the probability for the I
configuration is one over little n if
I is in the subset
n this is the subset n I've used it to
label both the number of elements and
also the subset itself P of I is just
one over little n if I is in n and p
subi is
zero
if I is not equal how do you write that
like that is not equal there not an
N that's what it means to say we know
the system is an N but we don't know
anything
else now what don't we have a more
interesting probability distribution or
more complex probability distribution
instead of having all of the
probabilities be zero
or uh all equal if they're not zero we
can imagine a more General situation
where we just have a probability p ofi
period it might be big in some regions
of the face or of the configuration
space it might be small in other regions
it might approximately be such that uh
that there's some subset here which all
have equal probability zero on the
outside may or may not be just some P of
I I would like some kind of measure of
the number of states that is included in
this probability distribution and I
would like it to be such that it counts
the state only a little bit if it's
improbable and counts it a great deal if
it's probable
I'm going to give you now a definition
of the entropy and I'll show you how it
works which is true for a general
probability distribution for General
probability and I I'll show you why you
use this in a moment but let's just uh
Define it
first the entropy for a general
probability
distribution is
minus the sum of all the states of the
probability of the I State time the
logarithm of the probability of the I
State let's see how it
works
um let's see how it
let's oh first of all do you know why
it's
minus yeah logari probability is always
less than one so the logarithm something
that's less than one is negative so this
is really a positive quantity this is
really a positive quantity log of p subi
is always negative Let's do let's do an
example let's calculate this let's go
back to the first example here in the
first example the probability was Zero
if you're not an n and one/ n one over
little n if you are an N so let's
calculate then s s is the
sum of all places so let's concentrate
on a point inside n here all right
what's the probability it's one over
little
n what's the log of the probability
logarithm of 1/
n there a minus sign and that's the
contribution for any one of the states
in
here right for any one of them what
about the states on the outside the
states on the outside give zero because
their probabilities are zero
all right 0 time logarithm of 0 is
0o logarithm is infinite for when p is
zero but uh p is but P log p is
zero uh so so you get for every
configuration in here you get 1 / n log
1/ n now what's the log of 1 over
n it's minus the log of n so we can get
rid of this and make it just log of
n but this is just a contribution from
one of the points in here how many
points are there in here n so we have to
multiply this by
n which is just equal to log
in so in the case where we have a
probability distribution which is zero
or one it reproduces the original
definition here of just logarithm of n
right uh what about the sit situation
where there is only
one point which has a non-zero
probability all the others being zero in
other words when you know with certainty
exactly where the system is in the phase
space in that case only one of the piece
of eyes is not equal to zero okay all
the other piece of eyes are equal to
zero okay so let's go to that uh that
one point which is not equal to zero
let's just label A J now minus or P
let's call it P sub z p subz log P subz
distribution is spread out over about in
States if it makes sense to say that
it's spread out over n States then it's
just logarithm of n otherwise a more
general definition which captures uh
which captures the two examples that I
gave and that's really all it's intended
to capture is summation of I P of log P
ofi that's definition of the entropy
okay as I said the bigger the entropy is
the less you know about the
system
uh what's the maximum entropy that this
system can
have why
one logarithm of capital N logarithm of
capital N would be the situation
where you know nothing about anything
and so each one of the states has
probability one over
B you know nothing and so it's just
logarithm of
capital
states yeah that's all you know you
don't know which of those States is
that's right you don't know which of
those States it's yeah yeah you you know
what the system is but you don't know in
which of the states the system it is
that's what maximizes the entropy
incidentally the difference between
maximum entropy and actual entropy is
called
information uh so um if you happened if
the entropy were exactly zero you would
have a lot of information you have a lot
of states and you know which one it's in
so the difference between maximum
entropy and entropy is the amount of
information available to you or it's
defined that way
okay so in some sense information and
entropy are opposite sides of the same
coin uh entropy is the information which
is unavailable to you because either
you're too stupid too lazy or whatever
it is that uh whatever reason or the
object is too small to see or
your whatever the
reason okay
that's that
is now what does entropy have to do with
entanglement that will come that will
come it is a measure of the uh of the
degree of
entanglement before we get on that we
need a definition one definition one
mathematical definition the mathematical
I'm going to give the mathematical
definition then we're going to take a
break because I'm getting tired we'll
take a break and then we're going to
come back and uh talk about the density
Matrix a little bit I don't think we'll
actually get to an tanglement eny
tonight but I want to set up the uh the
basic ingredients that go into
it basic mathematical operation done on
matrices and since matrices are linear
operators you can think of it as a
operation on uh on um on operators you
have some linear operator let's just
call it m m stands for
Matrix but uh can also stand for
abstract operator
and we and let's suppose we have a basis
a basis oh I'm going to
assume well no I won't assume um no no
assumption uh let's take a basis of
vectors in the space of States whatever
that space of states is let's call them
I and take the II Matrix the diagonal
matrix element of M
if m is a
matrix and this just stands for the i i
diagonal matrix element there's the 1
one element the 22 element the 3 three
element and add them all together that's
called the trace that's called the trace
of
M now you might
think that this depends on awfully much
on Which choice of basis vectors you
choose there are many choices of basis
vectors in a uh in a space you could
choose it was three-dimensional space
you could rotate your axes and so forth
I'm not going to prove this this is
something uh this is an exercise you can
either do yourself it's easy or you can
look it up in your favorite linear
algebra book the trace of a matrix is
independent of the choice of uh of um
basis vectors it's an invariant it's
quantity which does not depend on your
choice of basis
vectors and so all choices of basis
vectors give the same value for the
trace that's an important little theorem
uh and it plays an important role in
what follows but uh you look it up or or
prove it yourself it's not hard to
prove okay that's the definition of the
trace of M we're going to use that over
and over but supposing the Matrix in
some base
bis happens to be diagonal since it
doesn't matter what basis we comput it
in we can look for a basis in which the
Matrix is
diagonal if m is a Herm Mission operator
there will always be a basis in which
it's
diagonal if m is not Herm Mission it may
not be but if there is a basis where m
is diagonal then the diagonal elements
are nothing but the igen values of The
Matrix remember when a matrix is
expressed in diagonal form if it can be
expressed in diagonal form the entries
are the igen values of the
Matrix it may not have an inverse
because if it may not have an inverse if
any of the if any of the entries are
zero it won't have an
inverse yeah yeah but as long as the
entries are not zero we'll have an
inverse right okay good uh no actually
what it what it means is that it's a
function of a Herm Mission operator is
what it means uh but uh if it's diagonal
it's characterized by its igen values
and then the trace is nothing but the
sum of the igen values that's a way of
describing the trace which doesn't
depend on the choice of a
basis the igen values don't depend on
the choice of basis it's just if you
happen to If you happen to use the right
basis then the Matrix will consist of a
diagonal where the diagonal entries will
be the igen values but the concept of an
igen value is transcends any particular
basis so if you know all of the igen
values you add them up and that's the
trace of a matrix the sum of the Igan
values uh in particular of a Herm
Mission Matrix particular a Herm Mission
Matrix which always has a complete set
of igen vectors and igen values the sum
of the igen values is the trace and as I
said it plays an important
role let's take a break now for six to
seven minutes let's uh move
on let me tell you what the role of a
trace is where how it uh
[Music]
um let's let's go back for a minute to
the classical situation
the classical
uh
probability distribution some P
ofi let me just remind you that if you
have a p ofi and you have some
observable classical observable now a
classical observable just means some
function of the points in the
configuration space right some function
which takes on different values for
different states so we can call it f of
I an observable is just a function
of the configurations it just takes on
different values When You observe it you
find out something about which point
you're
at uh the average of f given a
probability distribution P sub I is of
course the sum over I
of P sub i f sub I you just weight the
different values of f with the
appropriate probability remember the
probabilities all add up to
one and this is this is the classical
this is the classical average or
expectation value of
f uh I'll just call it f I won't call
average of f that's the definition of
average of f
uh might we could also call it the
expectation value although it's not
necessarily
expected um the trace first let me the
trace is the analog of the sum over
configurations it replaces in quantum
mechanics summing over all the
possibilities so Trace becomes
uh uh or some over configurations
becomes Trace
some you'll see how it works as we go
along now there is a very similar
formula to this in quantum
mechanics which of course involves a
trace and in involves a trace of the
observable times something and that
something is called the density Matrix
and I'm going to explain it to you now
in a uh
uh in a in a very simple situation
first supposing somebody
prepares a state of a
system any one of the states of an
orthonormal basis
I behind your back somebody creates a
system in some State I but doesn't tell
you which state they've created it in so
it's definitely an electron or spin or a
composite system or whatever it happens
to be has been created by somebody else
in a particular state but all they have
told you is a probability distribution
for what state they created the system
in in other words what we could imagine
is somebody creating an electron by
putting it into a magnetic field and
that magnetic field could be up or it
could be
down and they tell you here's an
electron it's either up or down but I'm
not going to tell you which and I'll
give you a probability though 75%
likelihood that it's up 25% likelihood
that it's down this is not a situation
where you would write up plus down or
even 3/4 up plus one quarter down that's
not right but you know what I mean um
you wouldn't add the states together at
all with a definite phase you would just
say you don't know what state it's
in and the system is described
statistically with a greater degree of
Statistics than if it had been in
a then if you knew what state it was in
even if you knew what state it was
in uh certain measurements would still
be
probabilistic if you know what state it
was in certain experiments might be
definite and certain others might be
prob bistic but here has an added degree
of prob probability an added probability
aspect of things that not only if the
system was in a definite State might you
not know the answer to every question
but you might not even know what state
the system is in under those
circumstances you use an object called
the density Matrix instead of State
vectors density matrices are kind of a
looser concept a concept when you don't
know what state the system is in and
it's a probability distribution for
different states all right so let's
suppose that we have that somebody has
prepared the system definitely in one of
the basis States
I with a
probability let's call it row subi I'm
using row now instead of p uh just
because it's a standard convention for
this situation to call to call it row so
that's the uh row then is the
probability for the ey State now we can
make a matrix out of row right we can
make a matrix out of row and here's the
way I'll make a matrix out of
row I'm just going to this is the Matrix
in the I basis so this is IAL 1 IAL 2
IAL 3 i 4 likewise with the rows it's
going to be a diagonal matrix and its
entries are just going to be row row one
row two on the diagonal Row one row two
Row three
all other elements
zero the rows are real numbers they're
positive numbers because they're
probabilities and they're all less than
one and one more thing and this is
called incidentally this is called the
density
Matrix this it's called row and it's
called the density
matrix it's the analog In classical
physics of the probability
density uh what we call PAB body but
it's now just been organized into a
matrix with diagonal matrix
elements the elements are all
real and obviously they are the igen
values of this Matrix because whenever a
matrix is is has been written in
diagonal form the diagonal elements are
its
values one more thing you can say the
trace of the density Matrix is one why
is that because probabilities should add
up to one okay so if the sum of all the
probabilities adds up to one then the
trace of the density Matrix adds up to
one
now let's suppose we have some
observable let's call the observable
F and it's also a Herm Mission
operator we have an observable f
it's a Herm Mission operator as always
let me Define now the average value of f
if we had an ordinary state in other
words if we knew which state we were in
with probability one then the average of
f would just be the expectation value of
f in that
state if we were in the I State the
average of f would just be the
expectation value of f okay that's
obvious
right all right I say more generally
when you have this uncertainty about
which state you're in that the right
answer is that the average of F I won't
indicate it the same way I won't
indicate it by a bra AET because that
it's implicit in that that I have a
particular State I'll just write it as
the average of
f is equal to the trace of the product
of F and
row let's see if we can make any sense
out of that formula this formula is
quite similar to the corresponding
classical formula summation over I of f
sub I * P sub I similar formula Trace
being replaced or some being replaced by
Trace classical function being replaced
by an operator and the probability
distribution being replaced by the
density matrix it's called density
Matrix because it's like probability
density or probability yeah okay let's
let's uh work out what this thing is
let's let's work out what this thing is
uh the trace we can pick any basis we
like but let's pick the basis in which
row is diagonal for Simplicity assuming
that row is diagonal in some
basis uh then this just becomes the
trace tells us where's the definition of
the trace the trace tells us to take the
basis take the thing who Trace with
taking f * row and close it up again and
sum over
I that's the trace of ftimes
row okay now I'm going to do a trick
which we talked about last time we never
really used very much but I'm going to
use it now if we have a basis of States
then the unit operator can be
represented as the sum over the states
of
the diads made up out of the basis
vectors so let's and this what this
means is you can always stick an
expression like this between anything
else and not change it so in particular
I'm going to stick it between F and
row all right so that'll give us now we
have two sums to do one for the
definition of the trace and one for
resolving the identity this is called
resolving the identity by using a
complete basis of States so that would
give us on i f
j j row I summed not only over I but
also over J summed over I for the trace
summed over J to resolve the
identity good now
Row in the basis that I'm using I'm
assuming is
diagonal that means that I has to equal
J otherwise we don't get an expression
all right in that case this just becomes
the i i j Matrix element the sorry the
diagonal matrix element of row I has to
equal J we'll get nothing unless I
equals
J this just becomes row sub I the I
entry into the Matrix and this becomes f
i
i well what is this this is the
expectation value of f in the state r
this is the probability that the state
was made in configuration I and this is
just the sum of the expectation values
of f weighted with the probability
distribution to different
states okay so this makes sense to call
this the average of
f but we see now a uh a quantum
mechanical
version of this formula over here
in which as I said sum is replaced by
Trace and probability distribution is
replaced by
row here's a little theorem that you can
prove it takes two seconds to prove if
you have the product of two
operators A and B the trace of a * B is
the same as the trace of btimes a work
that out even if a and b don't commute
the trace of a product doesn't matter
which way you order them and so in fact
it doesn't matter which way you order F
and row trace of f time row is the
average
okay that gives us the concept of a
density
Matrix let's just look at some uh an
analogies with P first of all the sum of
P sub I should equal one
the analog is that the
trace of row is equal to
one trace of R is equal to
one so that's just another example of
trace and
sum being essentially the same
thing good now I'm going to give you the
concept the quantum mechanical concept
of
entropy is the quantum mechanical
entropy of a given density
Matrix now first of all the definition
is such that if you know what state
you're in only one of these rows is one
and all the others are zero then the
entropy is zero for any quantum
mechanical State any qu real quantum
mechanical state of the usual kind the
entropy is
zero uh the entropy is not zero not
because quantum mechanics has in it a
built-in probability istic aspect but
because you simply didn't know what
state the system was made in right you
weren't
told uh that's the source of entropy in
quantum mechanics lack of knowledge
about the state not lack of knowledge
even if you knew the
state okay the answer for the entropy
the definition of the entropy given a
density Matrix Row first of all here's
how you use it to calculate
averages but second of all the
definition of the density Matrix well
let's first write down the classical
formula the classical formula was Sum on
I minus of P sub I log P of
I well the answer is Trace minus the
trace of the density Matrix row times
the logarithm of the density Matrix
row what the hell is logarithm of a m of
a matrix
anyway well there's a general answer to
that but let me give you the answer in
the simple case where the Matrix can be
brought to diagonal form if the Matrix
in some basis is diagonal then the
logarithm of the Matrix is just the
Matrix made out of the logarithms of the
igen
values log of
row log row One log row
two and so forth and so
on all right so what is this this is of
course just the sum of the row subi log
row sub eyes exactly as it is
classically but I've written it in a
form now uh that uh that is
uh um that's more appropriate for
quantum mechanics as the trace of row
log row and so it has meaning in a
vector space not just as a classical
probability
distribution this is the definition of
the entropy
it has the property that if only one and
only one of the rows are non zero in
which case it has to be one because the
trace of row has to be one if one and
only one of them is non zero then the
entropy is zero okay 1 * log of 1 is
equal to zero if the probability
distribution is uniform all states
having equal probability that would be
the case where this would be
proportional to the unit Matrix then the
ENT y here is logarithm of the number of
states logarithm of the dimensionality
of the space of
States so if you know nothing about the
system you don't know how it was
prepared or anything like that then the
entropy is just logarithm logarithm of
the total number of states which means
the logarithm of the space of States
logarithm of the dimension of the space
of
states and that's taken over practically
directly from the classical concept of
entropy and it plays the same role it's
an indication of uh of lack of knowledge
of the system knowledge that you could
have but that you don't have in other
words the knowledge that uh that uh is
there to be
gotten but uh which you may have been
too lazy to
get what's all of this have to do with
entanglement well I think we're going to
have to quit now next time I'm going to
show you what this has to do with
entanglement but basically I'll just
outline it for you when you have a
system which is composed of many parts
or let's say two parts to be
specific you may be interested in only
one of the parts and not look at the
other part may have a
system which consists of two entangled
Parts they may or may not be entangled
in particular it's interesting when they
are entangled A and B
they're in some state which is an
entangled state of the two systems but
you're only going to do experiments on a
and ignore B alog together then the
question is how do you describe a
without reference to B there must be
some description that you can
use uh for a which contains all possible
experimental information that you could
do on
a if you're never interested in also
looking at B you don't look at B and the
answer is you use a density Matrix to
describe
a if a and b are
entangled then the density Matrix will
have entropy if a and b are not
entangled it will not have entropy so
one diagnostic for looking at a system
or at a composite system to find out if
things are entangled is to
determine what's called theang
entanglement entropy of the two systems
and it's a measure of how badly
entangled they are we'll come to it next
time and we'll work it out and we'll
work out some examples I want to work
out some real
examples uh to show you how entanglement
entropy codes the fact that systems are
[Music]
entangled the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at St stanford.edu